Now, to get our hands dirty by playing with Neural Networks intensible playground.
ではNNのIntensibleプレイグラウンドで 遊びましょう
In this Neural Networks playground lab,
このNNのプレイグラウンドラボでは
we will use intensible playground,
Intensiveプレイグラウンドを使って
to try and build Neural Networks to learn our data.
NNを構築してデータを学習させます
I want you to solve these problems in two ways.
これらの問題を2つの方法で解決します
First, we should try training our models using manual feature engineering,
最初は手動の特徴エンジニアリングを使用して モデルをトレーニングします
where we use our own knowledge to try and guess
ここでは独自の知識を使用して
the right combination and transformation of features to learn the data.
データの学習に最適な特徴の組み合わせと 変換を推測します
Next, we're going to hand over the reins,
次に操作権を
and add more layers and neurons using a simple set of
簡単な入力特徴を使用して
input features to see it can perform the feature engineering itself.
層とニューロンを追加し 特徴エンジニアリングの実施を確認します
Welcome back to intensible playground.
Intensibleプレイグラウンドに戻ります
In this lab, we're going to see if feature engineering
このラボでは特徴エンジニアリングが
can outperform our Neural Networks.
NNより優れているかを確認します
I have a feeling this is not going be the case. Let's investigate.
私はそうはならないと思います 調べてみましょう
All right. In this diagram here,
この図表では
we're trying to classify these blue and orange dots.This is a classification problem.
青とオレンジの点の分類を行います これは分類問題です
Which you'll notice, is that they look like two concentric circles.
これらの点は2つの同心円のように見えます
However, in this case there's a lot of noise.
しかしこのケースには多数のノイズがあります
So, therefore it is a lot of intermixing going on here.
そのため多数の混合が生じています
Okay. What I'm going to try to do is let's see how X1 and X2 to do in training.
ここではX1とX2がトレーニングで どのような動きをするかを確認します
As you can see, it's really not learning very much at all.
見てわかるようにほとんど学習していません
It's all kind of blurred together, it's pretty white.
全体的に不鮮明で ほとんど白です
So, therefore it's not one way or the other,
そのためどちらにもなりません
according to the scale down here, negative 101.
下のスケールによると-1 0 1です
So, it hasn't learned much. Let's see if you can do better.
つまりあまり学習していません 改善できるか確認しましょう
With feature engineering, I know this is a circle.
特徴エンジニアリングではこれは円になります
So, I do X1 squared and X2 squared,
そこでX1の2乗とX2の2乗を行います
and I try it now, let's see.
ここでやってみます どうですか
Wow! Look at that. Was going to ellipse.
見てください 楕円になりました
So, that means it's almost figuring out what this function is.
この関数が何かを もうすぐ把握できるということです
We know it's a circle, but however,
円であることがわかりますが
there's a lot of noise and everything.
多くのノイズがあります
So, it kind of offshores a little bit.
そのため少し外側にシフトします
Okay. Perhaps though, I can get my loss
しかしX1とX2を取り除いて
lower from 0.275 when we try to get rid of X1 and X2,
線形を形成すれば 損失を0.275から
the linear forms. Let's try it now.
下げることができます やってみましょう
Uh Huh, 2.85.
0.285です
Okay. So, it looks a little more circular.
もう少し丸くなりました
However, our test loss is slightly better.
しかしテスト損失が少し改善されました
Let's see now if we can do the same with Neural Networks.
同じことがNNでできるかどうか見てみましょう
So, let's go back to just X1 and X2,
X1とX2だけに戻りましょう
which as we saw earlier it did a really poor job.
すでに見たように 非常にひどい結果しか 出ていません
Let's add a hidden layer. Let's add two extra domains.
隠れ層を追加します ドメインを2つ追加します
As you can see here, it's having quite a hard time figuring out what this function is.
ご覧のようにこの関数の把握に非常に 苦労しています
The problem with that is, is that there is not enough capacity in these two neurons,
問題はこの2つのニューロンに 十分な容量がないことです
enough high dimensional representation to learn this distribution.
この分布を学習できるほど高次元表現では ありません
So, let's pause this here and see.
ここで停止して見てみましょう
Let's add another neuron.
ニューロンを追加します
Maybe this is enough capacity to learn this function.
この関数の学習にはこの容量で十分でしょう
Alright.
できました
It is still not quite getting it.
まだうまくいきません
Maybe, look at that.
これを見てみます
Took a long time,
時間がかかりましたが
but it's slowly figuring out that shape of the function.
徐々に関数の形状を把握しています
That's some kind of rectangular shape here.
ここではある種の長方形です
So, what this means is that we're kind of re-sailing on the cusp right here
つまりこの分布を示せるニューロンの量の
of the amount of neurons able to represent this distribution here.
変わり目をさまよっているようです
So, let's see if we can easier time if we just add one extra neuron.
もう1つニューロンを追加して
Alright. Look at that.
どうなるか見てみましょう
That was much much faster.
はるかに短時間で終わりました
We only have four neurons here.
ここではニューロンは4つだけですが
But let's see what happens if we add many many extra neurons.
さらに多数のニューロンを追加すると どうなるでしょうか
Alright. Let's see. Let's put a mold of four.
それでは4つの型を入れましょう
See what happens.
何が起こるか見てみましょう
That's train already.
トレーニングします
It's quite a lot slower here.
かなり低速です
There is a lot more mass to perform going through all these semi-layers.
これらの中間層の処理に多数の計算が 行われています
I think it's eventually going to get it.
最終的にはうまくいくと思います
I'm a little nervous it might overfit a little bit as you can see.
ご覧のように少し過学習かもしれません
It is no longer as a simple circular shape.
もう単純な円ではありません
Some crazy polygon here.
規則性のない多角形です
So, therefore it's overfitting the data and not doing so well on the test loss.
つまりデータの過学習で テスト損失に対処できていません
Which is much higher than it used to be.
前より高くなっています
Alright. Let's see some other distributions.
他の分布を見てみましょう
Here, we are distribution our classic Xr.
ここに標準の分布Xrがあります
When both X and Y are positive, or negative,
XとYの両方が正または負の場合は青になり
we have blues and when they're either r we have the orange class.
どちらかの場合はオレンジクラスになります
Let's see if we can learn this with just X1 X2.
これをX1 X2だけで学習できるか確認します
As you can see, just like before,
ご覧のように 前と同じように
Iq and X2 is not powerful enough to be able to describe this function.
IqとX2はこの関数を表せるほど 強力ではありません
It's basically zero all across the board.
ボード全体で基本的に0です
Let's see if we can figure this out using feature engineering.
特徴エンジニアリングでこれを把握できるか 確認します
With feature engineering, I'm going to
特徴エンジニアリングでは
introduce X1 X2 because I know that's what it looks like.
その見た目がわかっている X1 X2を導入します
So let's train this. Look at that.
これをトレーニングします 見てください
Very nice. It's a test loss of zero point one seven. That is great.
かなりいいですね テスト損失は0.17です 素晴らしい
Okay. Found it really easily,
非常に簡単でした
and here's my weight, 0.19. That's great.
これが重みで0.19です 素晴らしい
Yes there's been noise so we got some wrong,
確かにノイズもあるので間違いもありますが
but for the most part it got pretty much right.
大半の部分がかなり正確です
Let's see now if Machine Learning,
ではNNを使った機械学習が
using Neural Networks, can do a better job.
これより優れた処理を行えるか確認します
So we're going to put X1 and X2 back together,
X1とX2を戻して
and let's add a hidden layer.
隠れ層を追加します
So once again, I'm going to try to see.
もう一度見てみましょう
I want to have a small amount as I can.
できるだけ量は少なくしたいので
So I'm going try to get this down to just two neurons and learn this.
これを2つのニューロンにして学習させます
However, as you can see,
しかしご覧のように
it's not able to figure that out.
これを把握できていません
It's not enough complexity, not enough capacity in this model.
このモデルは複雑性も容量も不十分です
So let's pause this here and try add the third neuron.
ここで停止して3つ目のニューロンを追加します
Let's try training again.
もう一度トレーニングしましょう
As you can see here,
ご覧のように
it's having quite a hard time learning this function.
この関数の学習に非常に苦労しています
Now, maybe it's just on the edge,
おそらくもう少しでしょう
and I have to wait a little longer to see if it will learn it.
もう少し待たないと学習するかどうか わかりませんが
But it's kind of stuck.
スタックしたようです
Perhaps another initialization maybe will fix it.
初期化すれば直るでしょう
Let's see. There we go.
どうでしょうか
So, we tried everything, running initialization,
あらゆることを行い 初期化しました
and it will somewhat learn the function here.
ある程度関数を学習するでしょう
It looks more like like a diagonal hourglass a bit, actually.
斜めの砂時計のようにも見えます
However, that's not quite the function.
しかし関数ではありません
You can see the loss is much higher.
損失も大きく上昇しています
So, let's go to four,
4つに増やしましょう
that might do the job. Let's see.
これでうまくいくかもしれません
Here we are still with the arrow glass but it's becoming
まだ砂時計も見えますが
more and more like a series of squares.
一連の四角のように見え始めています
Which is what our function actually is. It's getting better.
それがこの関数です よくなっています
Now, let's see if I add a whole bunch more,
ここで大量に追加して
and see if we overfit it.
過学習になるかどうか見てみましょう
As you can see, it's a lot slower in it's training loss.
ご覧のように非常に低速化し トレーニングの損失も生じています
However, those are much more square shaped.
しかしかなり正方形になっています
This is looking great.
いいように見えます
Let's try another distribution type.
他の分布タイプを試します
Right here we have a spiral,
ここにらせんがあります
two spirals actually spiraling around each other.
2つのらせんが互いの周りを回っています
Much like a picture of a Galaxy.
銀河の写真のようです
So, let's see if we can train with X1 X2.
これをX1 X2でトレーニングできるか 確認します
I highly doubt we were able to.
おそらくできないでしょう
As you can see here,
ご覧のように
it really didn't learn the distribution at all.
分布をまったく学習していません
It's basically, pretty close to zero,
ほぼ0に近い状態です
and it can't decide what's what.
これが何かを判断できていません
So, what we can try is now some feature engineering.
次は特徴エンジニアリングを試します
Let's try.
試してみましょう
What do you think?
どうしますか？
Let's try circles, perhaps?
円を試しましょうか？
Nope. Let's try adding these.
いいえ これを追加しましょう
Will be sine and cosine,
正弦と余弦
or sineX1 and sinex2. It's trying.
sineX1とsineX2です 実行しています
I have six raw features going on here,
ここに6つの未加工の特徴が発生して
and it's sort of getting in.
入り込んでいます
As you can see up top,
上部を見ると
it's slowly gaining here.
ここがゆっくりと近づいています
There's a big gap here. I don't know where it's going.
ここに大きな隙間があります
It's really extrapolating very strongly here.
ここは非常に強く外挿しています
So, it's not really a greater job,
あまりうまく動作していません
it's kind of stalled out as you can see.
ご覧のように停止しています
Let's see if we can do this better with Neural Networks.
これをNNでうまくできるか確認します
Less turn this all off,
これをすべてオフにし
and else add a hidden layer.
隠れ層を追加します
Once we get started off with two neurons and see if we can do it.
2つのニューロンで開始したら うまくいくか確認します
As you can see here, it's really no much better than just having pure X1 and X2.
ご覧のようにX1とX2のときと まったく変わりません
It's not enough capacity to learn this model.
このモデルを学習する容量がありません
Let's go to three. See if you can learn.
3つに増やして学習できるか見てみます
It's doing slightly better than last time with extrapolation right here.
前回より少しよくなり ここに外挿がありますが
However, it's still not doing as good as just saving
この活性化した6つの特徴の保存は
all six features activated, or seven features.
それほどうまく行えていません
Alright. Let's see if we can add one more neuron,
ではもう1つニューロンを追加できるか 確認します
another layer perhaps. Let's see if this can do it.
層を追加します これでできるか見てみましょう
All ready. So, you can see we have
テスト損失に対して トレーニング損失が非常低く
a really low train loss for the test losses and doing so well.
うまくいっています
So, it's kind of stuck.
スタックしています
Let's try some more. Let's add some more hidden layers.
もう少し試します 隠れ層を追加します
Let's all put them to four.
すべて4まで増やします
Hopefully that's enough.
これで十分でしょう
Let's see what we get.
結果を見てみましょう
Alright. Both have gone down quite a bit.
両方ともかなり下がりました
However, it hasn't quite made a decision since the whole screen is white.
しかし画面全体が白いので 判断は下せていません
There it is. I have an inflection point.
そこに変曲点があります
My loss is going down a lot.
損失は大きく低下しています
However, you can see my test loss is also going up.
しかしテスト損失は上昇もしています
Now, it's going flat. So, this doesn't have enough capacity.
その後は平坦です やはり容量が足りません
So, let's go as far as we can go and add eight neurons each layer.
次は思い切って各層にニューロンを 8つ追加します
And hopefully, that's enough to learn this very complex and noisy function.
これならこの複雑でノイズの多い関数を 学習するのに十分でしょう
Alright.
できました
Let's try training this.
トレーニングしてみましょう
As you can see, it's going very slow when it's joining this train right here.
このトレーニングをここで結合するのに 非常に低速になっています
We're hoping that will finally figure out a way to make this function work.
最後にはこの関数を動かす方法が 見つかるはずです
So, my train loss is going down.
トレーニング損失は低下しています
How about my test loss? Is going up.
テスト損失は上昇しています
It's kind of leveling out, my test loss.
テスト損失はどちらかと言えば平坦です
When you're doing this yourself,
皆さんがこれを行った場合
your results might vary quite a bit due to
ネットワークのランダム初期化により
random initialisations of the network. Let's try a different one.
結果はかなり変動するでしょう 他のものを試しましょう
This one might be a little bit more promising maybe.
これはもう少し期待できそうです
Right, this is looking a little more promising.
これはもう少し期待できそうに見えます
So, you can see what it is doing, it's learning these ways over here. Fill it in.
これらをここで学習して埋めているのが わかります
What up? Looks like we overfit because now our test loss is diverging, it's not good.
テスト損失が分岐しているので過学習のようです これはよくありません
And there you go.
そうです
So, as you can see,
ご覧のように
even with this mountain network,
この山のようなネットワークでも
we are not able to learn that distribution very well.
この分布をうまく学習できません
We have all these extrapolations,
こうした外挿や
and broad guessing, and that's not going to do very well in our test loss.
広範な推測が行われ テスト損失の結果も あまりよくありません
Look at this.
これを見てください
Our test loss is going down all of a sudden. This is
テスト損失が急に低下しています 素晴らしい
great. Alright. It's getting more and more of the function learned.
学習した関数の量が増えています
However, it's going very slow due to how large this network is.
しかしネットワークが巨大なため非常に低速です
Remember, between each one of these layers,
これらの各層の間には
there is 64 weights between each one.
64の重みがあります
They have six layers,
6層あるので
I mean they have six times 64, just there.
6 x 64の重みがあります
Not including between my features layer and my upper layer.
特徴層と上層の間は含みません
Where I get another eight each.
そこには他の8つがあります
Well, there you go. Look at this. This is great.
これを見てください これは素晴らしい
So, I'm learning this function pretty well.
この関数をかなりよく学習しています
However, there are these extrapolations,
しかしこれらの外挿があり
interpolations going on here,
ここには内挿があり
where like this orange peak goes right through the spiral.
このオレンジのピークはらせんの中心を 通過しています
It's still getting slightly better and better over time.
時間が経つとさらに少しずつよくなります
As you can see, the test loss is getting lower and lower.
テスト損失は低下しています
However, this shape is very much overfit.
しかしこの形状は非常に過学習です
Now ready. As you can see,
準備完了です ご覧のようにようやく
we were finally able to find the shapes of all of these, using Neural Networks,
NNを使ってこうした形状を見つけることが できました
which is sometimes a better job,
らせんの場合はNNの方が
or the job at all in the case of the spiral,
適しているときもあります
was able to figure out its shape.
NNでこの形状を見つけ出せました